OK.
We will get started.
Now we're going to start the systems portion of the class.
So we've been doing a bunch of neural network stuff
for the last two lectures.
And now we're going to start getting into GPUs,
parallelization, and inference.
And systems, I think, is going to be, I think,
part of the stack that is most reasonable in a way,
in the sense that you can reason through all the pieces
and there will be kind of logical steps
that you can go through to get the result.
So it's very different and satisfying.
But when you first start interacting with GPUs,
it will feel a little bit like both magic and a very strange
device that you're interacting with.
I don't really know.
As a kind of class survey, how many of you
have taken a GPU programming class of any kind?
OK.
So this is pretty good.
That's a fourth, maybe a little bit less.
But I think when you first interact with these things,
it's actually a little bit of magic.
So it's good to understand.
And I think deep neural networks feel like magic,
but also, GPUs can too.
Sometimes people will show you plots like this.
I think my promise to you is that by the end of this lecture,
you will understand what this plot is
or why this plot looks the way it does.
And this is how much throughput you're
getting on a matrix multiply where
the x-axis is your dimension.
And you might think, well, maybe bigger matrix multiplies
are always more throughput because you have more work to do.
Well, you've got all these kind of crazy patterns happening
where, at certain sizes, your matmuls are much,
much slower than others.
Why?
You'll need to understand that.
You also need to understand some basics of how
to mentally think about a GPU in order to build fast algorithms.
And even if you're not a systems person--
I think probably not all of you, or even a majority of you,
are systems people.
But if you're thinking about architecture or just generally
reasoning about these things, you
need to understand the hardware model of how
your model is going to execute in order
to make an effective model.
Thinking back to Percy's initial lecture, a big part of scaling
is making sure you use your resources effectively.
And without understanding your systems,
you will never be efficient at using your resources.
And I am not a systems person.
Surprise.
And so before I start, I want to make
sure to point you towards resources
that I think are very good and very useful
and that I used in making this lecture.
Horace He has really incredible blogs and explainers
of how GPUs work.
There's an enthusiast group, CUDA Mode,
that loves to talk about GPUs and CUDA kernels and so on.
And there's a TPU and-- what?
GPU Mode now.
They changed their name.
OK, fine, GPU Mode.
And the TPU book, but now it's also
a GPU book by the Google folks, actually, this is a really incredible resource.
So if you're really excited or interested
by any of the stuff I talk about today,
I would strongly encourage you to look at that book.
And they also have exercises that you can work through.
And your assignment will have things
that look a little bit like those exercises.
So you can get a little bit of a preview of what
we will send you to later.
Great. OK.
So this lecture is going to be in three parts.
The first part is really, I would
say, just broad introductory material on GPUs.
This is going to be just the hardware
model, just how the programming of the GPU kind of
works, because the GPU is kind of a foreign device.
And I want you to understand philosophically how
they're different from CPUs.
And once you do that, we're going to talk about,
I think, six different tricks, important tricks,
to get a GPU to go fast.
These are just kind of building blocks
of how you can start to manipulate your code in order
to make it run efficiently on a GPU.
And then finally, the last part where we put all of this
together is going to be, we're going
to walk through FlashAttention.
And this will be our victory lap.
We will say, actually, at this point,
we understand everything we need in order
to reinvent our own FlashAttention
and to understand all the different components.
So that's going to be the goal that we're
going to be building towards by the end of lecture.
So we haven't gotten to scaling yet,
but from Percy's introductory lecture or just generally
following language modeling, we know
that if we have more compute on hand,
we can get better language models.
This is the currency by which we operate.
So if we have faster hardware or if we have better utilization
or we have more chips, and then we
have improved parallelization.
All of these can drive progress.
And so in some sense, the game for the last few years has been,
how can we bring more compute to bear in training models,
and I guess in the last year or so,
how can we bring more compute to bear
in the inference of these models.
So compute is just extremely important.
And systems is part of that.
So if we were talking about this in the '90s, I think the things
that we would be focusing on is clock speed.
We would be saying things like, well,
how we make computers go fast is,
we have a CPU that executes instructions serially,
and we make those instructions go faster and faster.
I mean, this type of scaling where transistors
got smaller and clock speeds got faster,
called Dennard scaling, held quite well for a while.
Really, the 2000s was about when this kind of scaling tapped out.
And one interesting side note.
The number of transistors, of course, has continued to go up.
But making transistors smaller does not necessarily
mean that your transistors go faster.
They don't move at a faster clock speed.
There's fundamental physical reasons why you don't actually
continue to get benefits of smaller and smaller transistors
at a certain point.
So this old approach of making your clocks faster,
making instructions execute faster, is not going to work.
So how do we get LLMs to continue to scale in this world
where we can't just make things faster in this frequency sense?
And that's where the GPU shows up
and parallel scaling, in general.
Percy's going to talk about more advanced topics next lecture.
But after that, it's going to be parallelism.
Parallelism and GPUs are both kind part of the same paradigm.
Instead of making things go faster serially with your clock
going faster and faster and faster,
instead you're going to scale horizontally,
have more things executing your instructions in parallel.
And so this is the story of GPUs.
This one slide, really, I think, or one picture,
summarizes the state of parallel scaling, which
is, in the early days of K20s and M40s,
you had respectable but somewhat pitiful by today's standards,
flops.
And all of a sudden, around P100s and V100s,
this curve takes off.
And you get super exponential scaling
in the amount of floating-point operations
that you can do year by year.
This is kind of a remarkable plot in the amount of compute
that we can bring to bear.
And so GPU scaling has really driven almost all
of the compute scaling that we've seen.
And we'll talk about all of the different components
that we have here.
I'll highlight them here just to put them into your head.
At the V100 era in 2017, we start getting tensor cores.
That's one of the big hardware innovations.
And then in the next few years, we're
seeing structured sparsity in FPGA and all these lower
number formats also driving our flops forward.
And we're going to see what that means in detail in a little bit.
So how is the GPU different from a CPU?
Those that have interacted with the GPU already know this.
We'll move on to more advanced things in a minute.
But for the rest of you, I think it's very important
to understand the model, the philosophy in some sense,
of how they're different.
So a CPU is designed for quick, serial execution where
you have complex branching logic, complex conditionals,
complex control flows.
Because of this, a CPU, generally speaking,
has really big control units.
And it has a few ALUs that can do
mathematical or other operations.
But this is meant to run very quickly.
So you want to go as fast as possible and have low latency.
The time between when you get an instruction
and when you complete it should be very, very short.
That's the general CPU design philosophy.
In contrast, the GPU is really about throughput.
And the plot on the right, I think,
is a great pictorial illustration of,
when you change these philosophies, what you end up getting.
So in a GPU, maybe you dispatch a task,
it takes a long time for it to finish.
It might be that you process a task,
and then you stop, and then you go work on another task,
and then you go back and work on another task.
But in general, even though your tasks don't finish quickly,
you're getting large aggregate throughput
across all of your tasks.
And what enables this is having tons
and tons of lightweight cores.
So a GPU has hundreds and hundreds of compute units
that are packed into a chip.
And all of these can execute in parallel.
So this is a very different mode of programming and thinking
compared to a CPU.
And I want to demystify what a GPU is.
I don't want you to think of it as a set of pieces
of text on NVIDIA-SMI.
I want you to be able to visualize
what the hardware is of a GPU.
I think this picture is, I think, usually
used as a pictorial illustration of what a GPU is.
I think this is a great logical picture of what's
happening inside of a GPU.
So a GPU, the basic unit of a GPU
is SM, a streaming multiprocessor.
And a streaming multiprocessor is kind of a core.
It's its own independent compute unit
that has subcomponents that it can use
to accelerate its computation.
And it has access to certain kinds of memories
that it can connect to.
So each SM, building on this idea of parallelism,
it's not a single compute unit.
It has streaming processors inside of it
that can then execute different threads in parallel.
But an SM is the discrete compute unit.
We'll see why later when I get to the programming model.
Each SM, you can think of as a core, almost.
And GPUs have tons of SMs.
An A100 will have 128 SMs.
Each of these can be independently programmed,
and they can independently execute different jobs.
And they have access to global memory outside of it.
And the other thing that we will see-- that's
the compute story of a GPU.
But we will see throughout this lecture
that a really, really important part of this story
is not just the compute part but the memory part.
Modern hardware and LLM optimization
is really defined by the memory.
And so we need to understand what the memories are
and where they live.
So when we talk about memory, there's different kinds.
There are different levels of caches
that are connected to a GPU.
There are registers, which are even more limited and even
faster.
And then you have global or high-bandwidth memory.
And as you can see from this table-- this is a benchmarking
that some folks did of, I think this was at A100 latencies--
the L1 and shared memory, these are very fast.
In something like 20 to 30 cycles
you can read and get data from them.
If you're hitting the L2 cache, much slower, and if you're
hitting global memory, that's 10 times slower than the L1 cache.
This is a big difference in your speed.
And this global memory is kind of what you normally
think of as a high-level programmer as GPU memory.
When H200 tells you I've got 144 gigs of memory,
you're talking about global memory.
You're not talking about shared or L1 cache.
Now, physically, where do these things live?
Well, global memory usually are these kind of memory chips
that live outside of your compute unit, whereas
L2 and L1 cache, they kind of live physically in the chip
itself.
So this is the picture of a GPU chip.
And you see all of these SMs.
These green blocks are SMs.
And you see L2 right here.
And the L1 is inside of each of the SMs.
So they're physically much closer to the compute units.
That's why their latency is so much better.
And you might say, OK, then if shared memory is so nice,
why don't you build a whole chip out of shared memory?
It's much more expensive, hundreds of times.
It's also much more power hungry from the way
that these memories are built.
And so this is the reason why if you're building
a practical accelerator, often you don't
want to just have a giant amount of shared memory.
You want to have this hierarchy of memory
and use it effectively.
I think Groq, which was recently acquired by NVIDIA,
was a design where you just have these giant amounts of SRAM.
And for certain workloads like inference, this is very helpful.
But still, for most accelerators,
you're going to have this hierarchy that you're
going to really have to respect in order
to make anything run fast.
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE] be shared memory in the L1 cache.
Yeah.
So the shared memory in the L1 cache, I guess,
operates differently.
The cache is really just a cache thing
that is storing recently accessed data elements.
Shared memory is a programmable element
that you'll actually interact with,
that you can put things in and out of.
OK.
Cool.
So that's the memory store.
And keep that in mind because it's going to keep coming back,
the memory hierarchy.
That's a really important object.
Now, we have the hardware mental model in place.
And now we're going to start talking about the software
and programming model of a GPU.
So there's three different important players
that live in the execution model of a GPU.
So there's a thread.
And if you're familiar with multiparallel programming
of any kind, you know what a thread is.
A thread is a lightweight thing that's running in parallel
and doing some work.
In a GPU, an important thing about the threads
is they follow the SIMT model, which
means that all of the threads that you have
are executing the same exact instructions.
They're going to have different inputs, which
means that the threads can actually
do separate useful work, but the instructions they execute
have to all be the same.
And this has important implications
for both the efficiency of your code
as well as the programming model.
If the threads can do all sorts of different stuff,
it becomes very hard to program.
GPUs are this tradeoff between programmability and efficiency.
Now, a block is a group of threads.
And the reason why a block is a relevant object
is that a block is guaranteed to run on a single SM.
And remember, an SM has a shared memory.
And so you can think of a thread as doing work in parallel.
Blocks have access to a shared pool of memory.
That will become very important later
when we talk about this idea called tiling, where
these blocks are going to be reusing
the same pieces of memory.
Finally, a warp is essentially the scheduling unit
of what is happening inside the GPU.
Threads are going to execute in groups of 32
consecutively numbered threads.
That is a warp.
This decreases the overhead of a scheduler
deciding which threads to run.
But essentially, these are the important three
terminology items for GPU.
I might say something like, oh, we're
going to have different warps executing.
That's what I mean here.
That's a basic unit of 32 threads that execute together.
Yes.
You mentioned that all threads execute the same instructions.
Is it all threads in a block or all threads in a warp?
All threads in a warp are going to get executed.
Cool.
Yeah.
So then the scheduler decides which warp
the next instruction goes to.
That's right.
Or, sorry.
The scheduler decides which warp is
going to be executing next and on what assignment and so on.
Cool.
And so in the memory model of a GPU,
device code can read from registers.
Registers are some of the fastest and most local items.
This might be storing things like memory addresses
of where you might need your arrays' start and end.
That's a place where you might store things in registers.
Then you've got local memory.
This is local, too, within your single SM.
You've got shared memory that can
be accessed within your block.
So if you have something you want to transfer across threads
or you want to have information that
is going to be reused across threads,
those are going to live in shared memory.
You can, of course, then read out, or sorry,
read from global memory, the DRAM
that's far away, as long as you're
willing to pay the latency hit of waiting for data
to come to you from global memory.
And there's also constant memory,
which I don't think I've seen very much
used in various programming things, that you can use as well.
Now, you can even transfer to and back from host memory.
When I say host memory, that means CPU memory
that lives on the machine.
You can do this if you need to offload
beyond the size of your GPU.
This is the set of things that you can do in your memory.
And really, the key thing, the most important part
of this memory model, is that as soon
as you go outside of your shared memory,
things are going to be slow.
So grouping the blocks to decrease
the amount of global memory reads
is going to be the name of the game throughout this lecture.
Now, I'm going to talk for three slides, two slides, about TPUs.
The majority of this lecture is about GPUs, mainly
because I think if you all go out and you write your code
and you build your models, it's probably
going to be on GPUs for most of you.
But I think it is very important that we talk about TPUs, both
because I think TPUs are cool and becoming more popular,
but also because TPUs are the alternative evolution of GPUs.
And you can see what's the same, what's not.
It's very interesting to see how TPUs work as well.
So actually, what's very interesting is
that TPUs are very similar to GPUs at a high level.
This is kind of convergent evolution.
If you want to build an energy-efficient accelerator
that does machine learning, you end up at the same place.
So the core mental difference between a TPU
and a GPU that you should keep in mind
is that TPUs are in some sense simpler.
They're more optimized for the machine learning workload.
They have lightweight control units.
And they have much bigger matrix multiply units.
And so they have the same basic structure
that I'll talk about for GPUs, where
they will have a specialized circuit to multiply matrices.
They will have components that can do parallel vector
operations.
And they will have some control system.
They have a very similar-looking memory structure
where they have slow memory, which is called high bandwidth
memory, and then they have an even faster local memory
called SMEM, or shared memory.
So this looks very, very similar to the architecture of a GPU.
Really, the difference is in how these things
are sized and the flexibility of these operations.
And, oh, and the main difference that I won't get into today
is the networking for these accelerators.
So if you're thinking about what is
the big difference between a CPU and a GPU,
actually, the biggest differences come in networking,
not in the individual chips because, really, the chips,
they live to just multiply matrices.
And this is from the JAX book, which
is a really lovely resource.
But they have these two tables.
They have a section on GPUs where
they describe how to essentially map GPU ideas to TPU ideas.
And whatever I say today about what's on the left here,
you can map directly to the TPU.
But the important thing at this point in the lecture to notice
is that for every concept in the GPU,
there's a corresponding concept in the TPU.
And this mapping is actually pretty precise.
A tensor core in a GPU, which is the matrix multiply unit,
corresponds almost exactly to an MXU,
which is a matrix multiply unit in the tensor core.
And if we're getting into really nitty-gritty details,
they actually use the same underlying circuitry.
They're both what's called a systolic array,
which kind of streams data in and out to do a matrix multiply.
So the architecture is very similar.
Now, how are they-- oh, sorry.
Yes.
Do you know what a typical [INAUDIBLE]
size is on the GPU versus TPU?
Oh, I do not know that off the top of my head.
I'm sorry.
I'll have to look that up.
Yes.
So the main difference between these two
is the number of different units that we have.
Oh, actually, I'll mention one very, very confusing thing
before I move on.
Sorry.
TPUs call their streaming multiprocessors
tensor cores. GPUs call their matrix multiply units tensor
cores.
They are named exactly the same thing.
So you will have to disambiguate them based on context.
If someone says tensor core for TPU, that means a processor.
If someone says tensor core for GPU,
they mean a matrix multiply.
So if you look at a GPU, a typical GPU like A100
might have something like 132 streaming multiprocessors.
That's a lot of processors.
A TPU will only have two units.
There's only two separate units running in parallel.
Now, the GPU, if we just look at the matrix multiply units,
will have 528 matrix multiply units,
whereas a TPU will have just 8.
And these are roughly scaled to be comparable-looking objects.
Why is it that it's this way?
Well, the TPU is relying on much bigger, smaller numbers
of matrix multiply units, whereas the GPU
is relying on smaller but much more
numerous matrix multiply units.
And you can imagine that if you have
a small number of many matrix multiply units,
it's going to give you more flexibility.
You can program them to do this and that.
Whereas a TPU, you're locked in to big, big matrix multiplies.
And so there was a funny situation in a recent paper
that I wrote where we did a batch size sweep,
and it goes all the way down to 64.
And it stops at 64.
Why is that?
Because the tensor core refuses to accept anything smaller than
a 64-dimensional input.
It has to be big matrix multiplies.
So this is the main difference.
But as you can see, GPUs and TPUs
share a lot of similarities.
They rely on a memory hierarchy between fast memory
and slow memory.
And they have a matrix multiply unit.
And because of that, the core concepts
that I'm teaching you today is going to transfer over
between GPU and TPU.
The basic ideas are always going to be the same for that reason.
And this is really convergent evolution.
There are only so many ways to cost-effectively allocate
memory.
And there's only so many ways to multiply a matrix very fast.
There's some design decisions that are different.
But otherwise, you end up at the same place.
OK.
Cool.
So that's TPUs.
And right, good.
And GPUs, I think, have been enormously successful
because it allows for easy scalability for things
like matrix multiplies.
If you want more throughput, you just keep adding SMs.
As long as your memory bandwidth can handle those SMs,
you get more and more throughput.
The programming is something we don't think about,
but it's deceptively easy.
If you were to try to write lower level, machine
code-looking stuff like PTX, it's actually doable
because it's all SIMT.
It's not like you're programming every single thread.
You're saying, OK, here are my instructions,
here are my inputs, now run them on all of my inputs.
It's something that maybe you all are already
familiar with things like applying or using
functional programming.
Finally, I haven't talked much about threads.
But whenever you're doing GPU programming,
these threads are always very lightweight.
They can be stopped, started at any time.
The scheduler can decide that, OK,
I have another warp that's better to run.
So I'm going to stop you and start this one.
And it's very quick to swap in these jobs.
That allows for much higher throughput
if certain jobs are stalled or have some property
that's lowering throughput.
So that's the benefit of GPUs as a hardware model.
It's been enormously successful.
And I think even in the early days
before tensor cores were implemented,
people realized that commodity graphics hardware,
this massive parallelism would be
very effective for scientific computing.
So this is one of the original papers
on using graphics hardware for fast matrix multiplies.
And this is a really, really cool hacker work.
People figure it out, well, we have these shaders
that are implemented, but we can program
specific shaders that will actually
give us matrix multiplies.
And different rendering settings actually
give us faster matrix multiplies.
And that's just really cool computer science things
you can do.
But nowadays, you do not have to do this.
You do not have to manually program your GPUs
to do matrix multiplies because as of the V100,
NVIDIA decided here is a piece of hardware that will do
your matrix multiplies for you.
And once that hardware existed, matmuls
became the one privileged operation in machine learning.
So at this point, there's a gigantic gap in the throughput
that you're going to get between parallelizable but nonmatrix
multiply operations versus amount of operations
you can do in a matrix multiply.
So this is one of the reasons why
any near future machine learning architecture
that we see that scales with compute
is going to have a matrix multiply in it because this the one way that you can really effectively get
a lot of compute throughput, more than 10
times faster than any other floating-point operation
that you can do in a GPU.
And then the last hardware thing that I'll end with--
I think this is the last slide of this section--
is that different components of the GPU
are scaling at different rates over time.
And we know that the GPUs are getting faster and faster.
This is just like a thing, as well as CPUs,
overall compute throughput is getting faster and faster.
So that's the gray line.
That's pretty fast.
We're getting faster and faster improvements
in the total floating-point operation.
Green is our memory bandwidth.
This is how fast we can transfer data.
That's growing comparatively slowly.
Blue is parallelism.
This is how fast we can connect different GPU devices.
That's also going very slowly.
And what does this mean?
This means that if you're out here in the early days of GPU
programming, probably you weren't thinking
much about memory because your compute wasn't that much faster
than your memory transfer.
But now as we go more and more to the right of this plot,
we're going to see a bigger and bigger gap between compute
and memory.
And that's why a lot of the optimization I'm talking about
today are memory optimizations.
As we go further to the right, we're
going to see memory and communication
bottlenecks more and more.
And so it's going to take more and more work to fully utilize
the hardware that we have.
So that was our very basic overview of GPUs.
I can't possibly give you a 20-minute lecture that fully
helps you understand what the GPU hardware is.
But hopefully, you have a flavor.
The mental model should be GPUs are massively,
massively parallel.
They execute instructions all at the same time.
Compute scale is really fast, really,
really fast, and even faster than memory, which means memory
is really important.
And because memory is important, everything we do
has to respect the memory hierarchy,
as much stuff that we do goes into shared memory and not
global memory.
So this is hopefully your understanding of GPUs.
And if you have this understanding,
at least you'll understand all the basics
necessary to internalize the next part of this lecture.
OK.
I can pause for a moment here in case people
have hardware questions or anything else
before I move on to the next part.
Yes.
So before V100s, there was no matrix multiply unit?
Yeah.
There was no tensor core that specialized to a matmul.
The tensor core is a V100 edition.
Before that, you would be programming manually.
Of course, you have so many SMs and so many
ALUs that you can still do quite good throughput.
But a specialized circuit for matrix multiply
really changes the game for that.
Oh, yeah.
Back there.
What's the difference between the shared memory
and the L1 cache?
The cache just operates on its own.
You don't get to control the L1 cache.
[INAUDIBLE] saw that L1 just because
of the physical distance.
Or does it also differ some other way?
Yeah, I mean, physical distance is a big part of it.
I mean, if I believe, if I remember right, they're both SRAM.
That's one of the reasons why global memory is much slower.
But the physical distance and the interconnects that are used
are the reasons why it's slower.
Yeah.
This is not inherent, by the way.
One additional side thing is that the equivalent to L2
cache in TPUs is much faster because they
make different design tradeoffs on silicon to enable that.
That's one of their selling points.
Yes.
If the compute memory gap keeps growing,
do you think that affects the way
future chips will be laid out?
Yeah.
Or maybe the future chip budget splits.
One of the things that I really didn't
want to talk about but now you forced me to,
is the inference landscape for hardware
is actually even more crazy.
So one of the things that people started doing,
I think last year, was something called
prefill decode disaggregation, where the prefill part, which
is very heavy matrix multiplies, is one chip, and then
the decode part for your inference, which is more memory
bandwidth-limited, is another chip.
And some of the models, I think, this was step 1-3,
which is a Chinese open-source model,
even has a thing where they try to disaggregate different
layers.
So an attention will go to one chip optimized
for one thing or one accelerator,
and then MLPs will go to a different accelerator.
And so you're starting to see, if this gap grows,
any clever tricks to utilize your very precious fast memory
becomes very valuable.
And you start to see this very heavily
in inference, which is even more memory-bound than training.
Yeah.
Cool.
Oh, yeah.
How many warps are in a block?
Do I know that?
I don't think that's on top of my head,
I think it's also hardware-dependent.
OK.
Good.
So the second part of this lecture
is now you all have a general sense of what a GPU is
and how it works.
Now we are going to talk about all of the basic tricks
to make workloads fast on a GPU.
These are kind of basic components
that you can put together to make things fast.
And to keep us motivated, one of my goals
by the end of this section is to explain this plot to you.
So this plot, as I said before, has a very simple picture.
It's the size of the matrix, a square matrix
that I'm multiplying.
I'm multiplying two square matrices.
And this y-axis is how many items I'm processing per second.
So this is the throughput.
And as I'm going to the right, in general, throughput
is going up.
Because I have bigger matrices, I have more work to do.
And so if I have a lot more work,
I can keep my hardware more utilized.
But there's all sorts of strange patterns here.
And we want to understand why are there strange patterns here
and how can we be at the very top of that curve rather
than the bottom.
So that's what I'm going to be talking
about in this second part.
And Percy already mentioned this.
This is the roofline model.
But the plot I showed before looks
a little bit like this classic roofline model.
This looks like there's a diagonal part and then a flat part.
And this is what we expect.
The roofline model says, up until a certain point,
we will be memory-limited.
We're memory-limited.
So no matter how much compute you give me, my throughput
is not going to go up.
At some point, you have enough work per unit of memory movement
that I can keep my compute units completely saturated.
And past that point, having bigger and bigger units of work
does not help me anymore.
No matter how much extra work you give me,
that doesn't help because I've fully saturated
my matrix multiply units.
So this is what we expect out of the classic roofline
model, where as we have faster memory,
we can push this upwards.
But there's a memory-bound region, which is diagonal,
and then a compute-bound region, which is flat.
This is kind of what we expect.
Now, if you want to make sure that your code runs efficiently
on a GPU, really, what you need to do is,
you need to be on this flat part.
As soon as we're at this flat part,
there's nothing else to do.
We're at maximum throughput.
So we want to prevent ourselves from being
in this diagonal part, which means we want to increase
the operational intensity.
The amount of computation we do per memory read
needs to be high enough.
So that's what we need to do.
And there's six different tricks that we will talk about.
Actually, some of these are not memory tricks,
the first one only.
There are six different tricks that
are maybe necessary to understand to make GPUs go fast.
The first one is a little bit different in flavor,
but then the rest of them will have
this flavor of trying to minimize memory movement as
much as possible.
The first one is a GPU-specific thing.
And it relates to one of the things
I said before, the SIMT model.
So in a GPU, every thread is executing the same thing.
Now, what happens if you write an if statement on a piece
of code that executes on a GPU?
On a CPU, it's quite clear what happens.
On a CPU, you will either pick one branch or the other,
you will execute that branch.
And you will move on with your life.
In a GPU, you will do something actually quite different
and slightly counterintuitive.
Every thread has to execute the same instruction.
So actually, every thread will execute both the if and the else.
But if you're not part of the if branch,
you will just mask out that computation.
You'll just sit idle.
And so whenever you have a conditional,
your mental model for the execution kind of looks like this.
Part of your threads will diverge based on this if statement.
Some of them will go to the bottom branch, some of them
will go to the top branch.
And the bottom branch ones will execute first,
top branch ones will wait.
And then the top branch ones will execute,
and the bottom branch ones will wait.
So in order to execute an if statement,
you're actually walking through both of these.
And then some of the threads are just
waiting, doing nothing if they're
on the wrong side of the branch.
And this is called control divergence.
And this is nice in some ways because it
simplifies programming.
It's not nice in that you now have these big compute
gaps where your GPU is doing nothing.
This is one of the reasons why you really do not
want to write if statements.
If you look at GPU code, if you have a ReLU,
you'll often find you're multiplying with zeros
or multiplying with masks instead of doing an if statement
where you're updating half because a multiplication is
going to all go at once.
And an if statement might actually
have to wait two clock cycles or something like this,
two operations.
So that's the first thing.
But, that's a separate story from all this memory
stuff, which is the main narrative or the main story of this.
The first one, which you don't really have to do too much for,
but I think is one of the most important ones,
and hardware-wise, I think where NVIDIA
is investing the most effort, is low-precision computation.
And if you look at this plot--
I've brought Bill Dally back to the slide--
this super exponential growth, where does this really
come from?
Actually, a pretty nontrivial part of this is number representations.
You start at FP32, you go to BF16, and then you go to Int8.
You just keep decreasing the precision of your numbers.
And of course, if you have half the bits,
you have half the bits to move.
And so you have your memory movement.
And so you've solved the memory bottleneck
for at least a little bit.
This is a dumb example.
But I'm just going to really drill it in there.
Let's say, I have a ReLU on a vector of size n.
If I'm on float32, I need to do one read to read my number.
I need to do one write after I've computed my ReLU.
That's going to be 4 bytes per operation, total of 8
bytes for my memory access.
I only have one FLOP worth of operation.
So that's 8 bytes per FLOP.
If I have the precision, of course,
I've halved the number of bytes per op.
I've halved the number of bytes that I need to move per FLOP.
Sorry, this is the inverse of arithmetic intensity.
Arithmetic intensity should be reverse of this.
Now, that's a very simple example.
But actually, how low precision works in a modern GPU
is actually very complicated and actually either very cool
or very crazy, depending on how you think
about how cool things are.
So when you do a matrix multiply,
let's say, you have a tensor core that's
operating in lower precision, how does that actually
work in practice?
Well, you're actually not going to keep everything
in low precision.
You're going to downcast before you take your product.
And when you sum up your partial summands
in your matrix multiply, you're going
to do this in full precision.
And then you might emit your outputs or your results in FP32.
And part of, I think, the reason why low precision is actually
kind of a black art is not because you can just
decrease precision.
Anyone can do that.
You have to figure out which of your operations
has to be in which number format.
So matrix multiplies, maybe both your weights and activations
can be low precision.
If I'm doing a softmax, maybe I need to do that in FP32.
Or if I'm doing an exponential, maybe that
also needs to be FP32.
Or maybe I can get away with BF16.
So I think it took several years, really,
to get low-precision training to be the state that it is today.
And a lot of that work was slow, incremental, empirical work
figuring out which of these operations we can downcast,
how we can downcast them, and how we can preserve stability
of training while making as much of our training
and inference low precision as possible.
People have been pushing this further and further.
I think once you think about how hard it
is to pay for fast memory, you realize,
if only I can cut my precision by another factor of 2.
People really, really want to do that.
And so FP8 was the next frontier,
I would say, of low precision.
Once you get to FP8, there's no longer
a standard, canonical format that everyone uses.
If you're using 16 bits, you're probably
using BF16 for a lot of what you're doing.
But with FP8, there's going to be
E4M3, which stands for four bits of exponent
and three of mantissa.
Or there's going to be E5M2, which is
more exponent, fewer mantissa.
Because these are used in different places,
there's no one-size-fits-all once you start to get to so few
bits.
But I think the thing that's really interesting
is the more advanced, low-precision number
formats that are coming out with the new hardware.
So I'll talk briefly about MXFP8 because it's both cool
and what it does to training is strange, to say the least.
So in FP8, the traditional version of training,
what you have is that all of, let's say,
activations are in 8 bits. So this is up here.
And then you're going to have a scaling factor in FP32 that's
going to allow you to scale this up and down.
Why do you have a scaling factor?
The scaling factor is necessary because you only
have four bits of exponent, let's say.
That's so few bits of exponent you're going to quickly over
or underflow.
So you need the scaling factor to keep you in the right range
so you can keep some information.
Well, people realized this is not optimal
because a single matrix might have very different magnitudes.
One part of my sequence might have much bigger activations
than another.
So instead of having a single scaling factor,
why don't we have many scaling factors?
So MXFP8 and these multiscaling factor formats
that are much more advanced now have many scaling factors.
Each of these scaling factors corresponds
to the relevant colored submatrix.
So the first four elements in this matrix
correspond to this first scaling factor and so on and so forth.
Now I have more scaling factors, these scaling factors
are actually going to be in lower precision.
These are going to be 8 bits as well.
They're going to be E8M0.
So they only have exponent bits.
So they're all powers of 2 in 8 bits.
So you have to make these tradeoffs.
Now, what was I going to say?
OK.
So MXFP8 is going to use more mantissa in the elements.
Scale factors are themselves FP8.
And you're going to have one scale factor every 32 elements
in your matrix.
OK.
I'm going to pause here.
Don't read the third thing.
Now, think for a moment.
What is the problem with this design?
What is the big issue if you do something as clever as this?
So the big issue here is-- let's say,
I want to transpose this matrix.
The transpose of this matrix does not
have the same pattern, so to speak,
scaling pattern as this matrix.
And so now it used to be that a transpose of a matrix
was simple.
I just transpose this matrix.
I don't have to requantize.
I don't have to do anything.
Transposing this matrix is very complicated
because I now have to potentially requantize
this whole matrix to fit this 1 out of 32 pattern that I have.
And so what happens internally when you actually use MXFP8--
and I found this to be crazy but also kind of cool--
is that when you're training your model with this thing,
it actually creates two copies of every quantized matrix, one
for your original matrix, one for the transpose.
So if you ever want to transpose,
you have the transposed version waiting for you.
And that's how you get around this, which I think
is a crazy and cool thing.
The point here is maybe not to emphasize the GPU trivia.
But the point here is that once you
start getting to these FP4, FP4 formats,
things start getting pretty exotic because the amount
of exponent and mantissa loss that you
have are pretty extreme.
So you have to be very clever about how you do this.
And as I said, if you were to go and really train a model, FP4,
which I think a lot of frontier labs
are doing for the compute benefits,
you have to be very careful.
This plot does show what I was saying.
So every time you quantize, you're
going to quantize one way, and you're
going to transpose and quantize.
So you're going to have both copies.
And then the other part, which I told you about a few slides ago,
is you're only going to quantize certain layers that you
think are safe to do so.
And this is another trial and error thing
that you have to figure out.
But once you have all this together,
you have the big benefits of training an FP4, which
is that when you're doing those matrix multiplies,
you're probably going to get 20% to 30% savings, maybe more,
depending on the size of your matrix.
Unfortunately, it's not going to be a 2x speedup because you have
to do all these quantization operations.
There's a big overhead doing this.
So it's not free.
Yes,
I remember reading that the first layer and the last layer
are very hard to quantize.
Do you have any intuition about that?
That's right, that's right.
I do not have intuitions for the first layer.
The last layer.
I think, being hard to quantize is because it
is a first-order factor.
It drives a ton of the loss.
And so I think you end up getting both instability
and big loss increases if you attempt to quantize the very
last layer.
I put this up there almost because I
think it's so ridiculous.
The next frontier, this is already implemented as MXFP4.
The entirety of MXFP8 can be shown to you in this slide.
It's negative 6 to 6.
You have all the possible values.
But now that you understand MXFP8,
you can also understand how this thing works.
You're going to have a structured block,
where each block is going to be one of these four bits.
Every 16 of these numbers, you're
going to have one scaling factor.
And that scaling factor will itself be FP8.
This is an E4M3 scaling for those scaling factors.
There has been a paper that has trained with FP4.
I don't think I've heard of anyone successfully training
in the wild, real, big, serious models with FP4.
But I think this is coming.
The next generation of models will probably be FP4.
So that was low precision.
I think it's really cool that you can really
push the limits so far that you're ending up with just plus
6 to negative 6, and yet you can do interesting things
with matrices in that precision.
Oh, yeah, there's a question.
So is this only for matrices that you can apply this,
not just single scalar step?
Yeah.
So you can quantize anything.
You can quantize the activations after a ReLU, for example.
But there just isn't as much of a need to.
So like a matmul, if you quantize that, you can get really
big throughput improvements.
And that's why if you look at the MXFP8 training one,
these are all matmuls that are getting FP8 quantized.
The overhead is probably not worth it
for most of [INAUDIBLE].
This has something to do with the hardware.
It's not like the matmul hardware part only does this.
Well, it's not exclusive to that.
Yeah.
You can always do lower precision stuff.
And then it will decrease your memory movement.
This is true.
But for the others, it doesn't quite make sense.
This isn't any hardware limitations?
It's not a limitation.
But there is hardware support for all of this.
So it is baked in.
A bunch of this is baked into the hardware to accelerate it.
Yeah.
You positioned this as an improvement for memory bandwidth
or loss, requiring less memory bandwidth.
But is there a benefit in this one?
Yes, yes, for sure.
For compute, you get basically linear improvements
for just multiplying the quantized numbers.
But the fact that you have to quantize and dequantize
means that the benefits are more diluted.
Yeah.
Do you have to train the scale factor?
The scaling factor is an implementation-dependent choice.
Depending on the library, for example,
you might get different ways of quantizing and dequantizing.
Training is a strong word.
But you might have quantization factors
that scan through and pick the max, min.
Or you might have scaling factors
that look at historical running statistics and then use those.
I wouldn't really call them training per se.
At inference, you might fit them more precisely.
So there's no gradients.
At inference time, you might.
At training time, you would not.
Yeah.
Has anything been done with structured sparsity?
Because I guess NVIDIA had it.
Yeah.
There's a lot that's been done with structured sparsity.
And I mean, MOVs, I think, is one successful example
of a structured sparse operation that people use.
Yeah, right.
So I mean a lot has been done.
Chris Re here has done a lot with lots of different kinds
of structured matrices.
I think the benefits of that in terms
of the compute benefits versus the representation losses,
I think has washed out.
I don't think it's a bad idea.
But empirically, it hasn't, I think, necessarily panned out.
Oh, yeah.
A lot of squeeze that we've been talking about quantizing models
for decades.
What is the current approach?
Is it train in full precision or half precision and then distill
into a quantized model that you can run on your Apple computer
and things like that?
What it's like [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah.
I mean, there's a combination of-- you probably
want to train a bigger model and then quantize down.
There's various kinds of quantization, scaling laws,
and papers that people have written,
precisely characterizing the tradeoffs here.
I think the state-of-the-art involves combining both
quantization-aware training, to some extent,
and model scaling with post-training quantization
of various kinds.
Yeah.
There's a lot that I think is not fully well understood.
Even industry teams that I've talked to
are talking about still doing science of quantization.
Yeah.
OK.
So the other trick--
this one is much more of a conceptual programming thing--
is operator fusion.
It's a fairly simple idea.
But you'll be surprised at how much this doesn't already
happen.
So think of a GPU as a factory.
You've got your memory warehouse.
And you've got your little compute factory.
And you've got a little belt conveyor going back and forth.
If you scale up your compute, you're
going to be bottlenecked by your little belt conveyor.
And this will be worse if you have many operations.
Imagine I've got lots of different operations I need to do.
And I'm going to ship my raw materials to my factory
and back and forth and back and forth.
This is a lot of memory bottleneck that you're
paying for, and lots of duplex bidirectional memory bandwidth.
Now, wouldn't it be better if I just had one giant
factory that would take all the raw materials
and ship back my finished product?
This way, I only have to pay for memory bandwidth twice.
Very simple idea.
This is operator fusion.
And this appears very often.
If you write a very simple, let's say, computation of sine
squared plus cosine squared, what
does the PyTorch computation graph look like?
It looks like this.
You got your x, I do my sine, I do my cosine.
I square it on both sides, I add them.
And I get my output.
Naively, if you don't do anything smart,
what this will do is each of these
will be a factory, so to speak.
You will read and write from global memory
each time one of these is called.
And you will incur quite a bit of memory cost
every time you do so.
So this is pretty painful.
And you can imagine instead of doing
that, why don't I just write GPU code that reads once
from global memory, does the whole thing inside the SM,
as I talked about before.
And then after it's done inside the SM,
I'm going to write it back to global memory,
a single kernel that does all of these operations.
This is called fusion.
And anything that's easy like this-- this is a very easy fusion.
It's like a graph that I can just squish down
into a single unit--
a compiler can automatically do this for you.
So Torch compiler, which is a compiler for PyTorch, or JAX
compiler, which is JAX's compiler, which
is more deeply integrated into JAX, both of these
will fuse these kinds of basic things into a single CUDA call.
I'll talk a little bit more about fusion later.
The advanced version sometimes requires manual intervention.
But the simple versions, you can just think of as compilation
will solve your problems.
The third idea is recomputation.
So we know in back propagation, what
do we do, well, we go forwards, upwards on the tree.
This is from Percy's 221 class.
You go upwards on the tree.
And you keep track of activations.
You store these little activation numbers.
And then when I go backwards, I'm
going to use the activations that I
store to compute the backward signal down my tree.
We all know backprop to some extent.
So we all know what this is.
But also, now we're looking at this
not from the perspective of mathematics,
how do we compute a gradient.
We're thinking about this from the perspective of systems.
How do we minimize our memory?
Well, if we think about what's happening,
let's say, I have something simple
I have x sigmoid, sigmoid, sigmoid out,
each of these sigmoids is going to generate in the computation
graph some residual or some activation
that I need to track.
So after my first operation, I have S2, second operation, S1.
And then when I need to do my backwards pass
it will consume S2, S1, and my output, or sorry, the gradient
at my output.
And I'm going to push this backwards towards the derivative
of my input.
So if I count the number of memory reads and writes,
it's going to be one memory read for x, three memory
writes for S2, S1 out.
And then on the backwards pass, this is flipped.
So this is a total of eight memory reads and writes,
very low arithmetic intensity because I'm just stacking a bunch of sigmoids.
Now, what can I do instead?
Well, what I can do is, I can just throw away
all of the activations.
Normally, you wouldn't do this.
Why would I want to recompute something?
But imagine you're in a world where computation
is super, super cheap.
You just have abundant computation.
You're not using all of your units.
But your memory is very expensive.
Any read and write has a lot of penalty.
Then you might prefer this computation graph
where I read an X, and then I'm going
to do sigmoid, sigmoid, sigmoid, output.
I'm going to store this output.
I have to write this because that's the output of my graph.
But now in the backwards pass, my backwards graph
is going to get in D out.
And on the fly, I'm going to reforward the X
and then compute the activations on the fly right
where I need them.
So now this is going to be two memory
reads for the D out and Dx and one memory write for the Dx.
So I've gone from eight total memory accesses to just five.
So now I have 5/8 the total memory accesses,
same computation.
But I've spent a little bit of extra compute
and saved a little bit of extra memory.
This is another very important trick.
We don't normally think about this
because usually, we're concerned with just
computing the gradient.
But once you have a systems mindset,
you start to think about recomputation.
Cool.
Trick number four.
This is another memory trivia thing but surprisingly becomes
important and also why sometimes it's
important to understand the hardware model of what
you're interacting with.
So global memory, which is the big memory that lives
outside the chip, is DRAM.
And DRAM, because of the way that it is structured,
actually comes in bursts.
What that means is, when I access,
let's say, the very first position,
I don't actually get just the first value.
I can read off all four of these first values for free.
And that's because the way the memory cells are lined up,
there's these blocks of memory units.
And then when I activate an amplifier,
I can just read out all of these almost for free.
The way that it's structured in parallel
allows me to read blocks of memory.
That makes sense as a hardware model.
And so this is called a burst section.
And so whenever a section is accessed,
all the other locations can also get delivered for free.
And you won't pay for them, so to speak.
And so you might have something like 128 bytes worth of a burst.
That means a single read will return, potentially,
128 bytes worth of data, as long as it lives
in the same contiguous block.
So this means that if you have your reads arranged contiguously
where they're all together, it's going to go much faster.
And to use a term, you say that a memory access is coalesced.
So that word means if all of the threads in a warp
fall in the same burst.
So what that means is, let's say, I have three threads.
And all three of my threads, sorry, four threads, and my four threads
live inside of a single burst section,
or they're reading from this burst section.
Then this is coalesced because they're using up all
of this entire burst section.
And I'm fully utilizing this very nice property
of DRAM memory.
And so if I have multiple warps, I'm
going to have different multiple burst sections.
But you can efficiently read out of memory
by grouping together your memory reads.
Yeah.
Why does the memory access have this pattern,
like this T shape pattern?
Which one, like this?
This one.
Yeah.
So as far as I understand, the memory cells
are arranged in a grid.
And your amplifiers are deciding which cells
to read, operate at a column-wise level.
And activating the voltage for this often a thing that takes a significant amount of time.
So once you've selected the column,
readouts of multiple elements within that column
are much comparatively cheaper.
But this is to select, to read that upper red cell.
Yeah, right.
So if I want to read this, for example, I'm selecting this.
Or maybe it's columns that are cheap in this diagram at least.
But if I'm trying to read this, I
might get this whole row for free
because I've addressed this whole row.
You don't get a T for free.
Yeah.
OK.
Good.
So you're saying like, Tatsu, why
are you telling me DRAM trivia?
The reason why I'm telling you DRAM trivia
is because-- think about matrices.
Matrices, you often want to read in big blocks
because you're going to do matmuls.
And certain kinds of memory accesses on matmuls
are privileged.
They're much more nicely structured than others.
And sometimes you can take advantage
of this to get very, very fast memory reads.
So the mnemonic or the thing that I remember
is, if you have threads and you have a row major matrix,
so it's sorted where each row is how your indexes are increasing,
threads that move along the major axis are not coalesced.
And to really make this visual-- actually,
I like this diagram on the right.
Imagine I have this 4 by 4 matrix.
This is row major.
So it's sorted in the order of the yellow block comes first,
the red block comes next, and so on and so forth.
This is the linear ordering in memory address.
This is the matrix that I'm trying to store.
Now, imagine that I have threads that
are trying to read each column, each clock cycle.
So I read a column, I move to the right, I read a column,
I move to the right.
If I'm doing that at the very first iteration,
I hit this element, this element, this element, this element.
Notice that each one of these land in a different burst window.
And I've read the entire vector, so to speak,
or the entire matrix, sorry, so to speak, even though all I
wanted was a single column.
Now, imagine if I was reversed, if I was flipping this matrix,
I could read the entire block.
Every thread would get its read in a single read of the memory.
So coalescing can give you significant improvements
in reads from large, contiguous structures like matrices.
So this is one reason why you might
want to think a little bit about row versus column
versus other kinds of ordering.
The last one that I want to talk about--
and this is the big one and maybe the most important idea,
I've saved it for last-- is the idea of tiling.
And I think this one has probably the big impact
on performance.
Tiling, I think, more than any other idea,
is this idea of trying to do as much as you can
with the memory hierarchy.
So what we want to do is, we want to group our memory
accesses as much as possible.
And shared memory accesses should be done together,
and they should be done on shared memory.
So the reason why it's called tiling
is I'm going to cut up the things that I need.
I'm going to tile my space.
And each tile will be loaded into my shared memory.
And once that tile is loaded, I'm
going to repeatedly read from that tile
and do as much as I can.
So let's think about the matrix multiply case.
I want to multiply this matrix and this matrix.
And this matrix on the right bottom, this is my output.
This is where I'm writing my matrix out.
This is a pretty standard notation for this.
Now, if I want to do this, I'm going
to be reading as I'm reading through the threads
multiple-- sorry.
The same entry will be read multiple times.
And to be precise, each entry will be read N times in an N
by N matrix multiply, naively.
So you might think, if I'm reading
this entry, let's say, M0, multiple times, instead
of hitting global memory each time,
why can't I group all of those memory accesses together?
And the nice thing about matrices
is that there's a very natural grouping.
And this is to essentially cut the matrix up into submatrices
and then load them and then operate upon them.
So here is a very simple algorithm.
I'm going to cut out my matrices into 2 by 2 submatrices.
And then I'm going to load different tiles.
So I'm going to first load the M 0,0 tile, the top left here.
I'm going to load the N 0,0 tile,
the top left of my top matrix.
And I'm going to load those into shared memory.
So I'm going to pay the cost of transferring those
slowly from global memory once.
But once they're in shared memory,
I can read and write very fast with those tiles.
This output tile will also be, for now, in shared memory.
And I will operate on these submatrices entirely.
So I'll multiply these two submatrices.
And I'll put the partial sum into my output submatrix.
So that allows me to do a bunch of reads
and writes all in the shared fast memory.
And then I can write it back out when I'm done.
What does the math look like?
Well, in the nontiled case, I already told you,
each element of my input is going
to have to be read n times when I do this big N by N matrix
multiply.
If I tile them with a tile size of T,
then each input is going to be read N over T times
from global memory and then T times within each tile.
And this makes sense, the extreme.
If T is equal to N, I read it once
from global memory and access it N times in shared memory.
And this is great because the T times reduction in global memory
access.
If you have big, big shared memory tiles,
it means that you can dramatically
reduce your global memory access on something like a matmul.
Cool.
OK.
Yes.
Are you doing this because you can't put that entire block?
Yes, yes.
That's right.
But if you were building one of these very fancy
alternative accelerators like rock or something,
which is all SRAM, then yeah, you just
put the whole matrix in there.
And you're very fast for the whole thing but very expensive,
very, very expensive.
Yeah.
And then this also happens at the GPU level
too because there's context switching where I can't even
fit a tile into one.
And then you just keep adding that tile again and then again.
Is that how it works?
You mean, like, are you asking whether this kind of splitting
happens at the accelerator level?
tile across the GPUs.
This will be one tile.
That's right.
Yeah.
So data parallel, you can think of as this.
If I have data on this axis and weights
here, if I cut it on one of the axes that's
kind of data parallel, tensor parallel
could be another kind of parallelism.
All these parallelism look a little bit
like tiling in some ways.
Yeah.
Cool.
OK.
Oh, yeah.
So for the previous one, can I assume
that a library like PyTorch will just do that automatically?
Yes, yes.
So like any matmul kernel that you
call will do tiling underneath.
Yeah, that's right.
If you're doing some exotic operation,
you might want to think about tiling like, things happening.
You want to be able to locally reuse your reads.
But I will say even PyTorch or something is not perfect.
And so we will talk about some of the imperfections that
will happen.
So tiling is very, very powerful as an idea,
but it's also complex.
You can actually end up with some really subtle things
happening with tiles.
So imagine I have a tile size of 128, 128.
If my matrices are 256 by 256, life is good.
I've got four tiles, perfectly cut.
Now, imagine I increase my coordinate size by one.
Now, I've generated two very skinny tiles with basically
nothing inside of them.
So now you realize, actually, this tile sizing thing
is actually pretty complex.
Depending on my matrices, I might
need to adjust my tile sizes to somehow trade off
my memory bandwidth versus this gigantic empty space
where I'm doing nothing.
The tile sizes is actually a thing that you optimize.
So coalesced memory accesses, the size
of your shared memory in your accelerator,
and the sizes of your matrices all
affect which tiles are optimal.
And if you know about different options in PyTorch,
there's a compiler option called max-autotune.
I don't know how many of you have used this or know about this.
You turn on that flag.
For the next 15 minutes, PyTorch is
going to run an endless series of benchmarking tests.
And you'll realize, actually, what it's doing is,
it's trying all sorts of different tile sizes
on your matrices and trying to figure out
which one is actually faster.
And you'll find that you'll get nontrivial benefits
from actually optimizing these things.
The other thing that you'll find related to coalescing is,
or if your matrices are the wrong size, what you can do
is that your attempt to read a tile might actually
trigger a lot of memory reads.
So imagine I have this nice world where I have, let's say,
this blue one is the row.
And I want to read this nice tile.
And my burst sections are the width of the tile.
In this case, if I do four reads, I'm good to go.
Because of the burst sections, I read this entire submatrix,
so good memory reads from coalescing.
Now, imagine I shift the matrix size by one.
Now I've bumped this first row over.
So this blue box now lives over here.
And there's no way for me to coalesce my reads
to read a single tile in one go because now all these things are
ragged and misaligned.
So I need to do at least two tiles worth of reads
to read out this one tile.
So there's actually a lot of complexities involved
in optimizing tile reads once you
start thinking about coalescing and all these other things.
And so in this case, what you have to do is padding
in order to line up, essentially,
the boundaries of the burst sections with the tile
sizes that you have.
And this is why you end up getting stuff like this,
which seems very mysterious.
I think this is one of my favorite weird ones.
Andrej Karpathy, when he was doing nanoGPT speedruns,
said well, when I increase my vocab size from 50,257 to 50,304,
I got a 25% speedup.
And it's kind of weird to have to pad in order
to get a speedup.
But maybe it makes sense once you realize things like this.
Padding can start to shift the rows and columns so that you
actually get very efficient reads, whereas at other times,
you do not.
Yes, go ahead.
Is there a usual tile size that you
should be taking into account?
You don't want to think about tile sizes per se,
because tiles, you should normally
think of as a lower level systems thing, unless you're
writing your own kernels.
But you do want to think about the size of your matrices.
But you want the size of your matrices
to be divisible by the tile size.
Right.
So you want it to be—I'll talk about that in a moment,
but right, generally, powers of 2, ideally divisible also by 32.
OK.
So now we can talk about this matrix mystery over here.
We have essentially all of the pieces
that we need to understand this.
So we'll walk through this one by one.
We've already talked about compute intensity,
the roofline plot.
You need to have enough work for each memory read
in order for you to be able to saturate your compute unit.
That's what's driving this diagonal upward trend.
So that one is done.
Now, let's talk about some of the other ones.
First one's tiling.
If we look at each of these lines
and we color them based on, essentially,
the divisibility of the matrices,
you will find that the blue ones are essentially only
divisible by 1.
They're not even even.
Orange ones are divisible by 2.
Green is divisible by 8, red is 16, and then purple is 32.
And you see that the ones that are not divisible by 1 or just 1
or just 2 actually have very bad throughput.
But once you start to get to higher multiples,
you start to essentially get no diminishing,
sorry, no penalties.
16 or 32 perform equally well.
And it's not because of somehow powers of 2
are magic or something like that.
It's because 16 and 32 are sufficiently
large that it has the right burst window property.
It fits the whole burst window in.
And so you can get coalesced reads into your entire tile.
And it has a major impact on alignment.
Now, if we look at what's remaining, if we look
at this orange line, we'll sometimes
see this weird periodic behavior where, suddenly, performance
will drop.
And this is very weird because I'm just multiplying matrices.
Why does adding a single extra dimension
suddenly kill my throughput?
And this is, I think, using all of the things
that we learned is kind of fun to get to this end.
Percy calls this GPU trivia.
So I think he hates this one, but I love this one.
So why is it that going from here to here,
I get such a big drop in throughput?
Well, it happens between 1792 to 1793.
And why does this happen?
Well, I'm using a tile size of 256 by 128.
So that means, how many tiles are there?
Well, there's 98 at 1792.
But once I bumped myself up to 1793, well,
actually I've increased both tile sizes by one.
So I now have 120 tiles.
So I have 98 tiles before, and I have 120 tiles now.
That's bad, but it's not this bad.
This drop is gigantic.
Well, it turns out the reason why
it's so dramatic is because the A100 has 108 SMs.
And 98 tiles fits in 108 SMs.
But 120 tiles does not fit in 108 SMs.
And so you finish doing 108 SMs and you're, well, I've
got 12 more of these guys.
I got to, I guess, process them.
And most of your GPUs sitting idle.
So you can end up with these very weird effects once again,
where by bumping up your tile size by one, suddenly,
you need to wait a whole other cycle for you
to process a bunch of tiles.
And that's called wave quantization.
So that was all for part two.
How do we make machine learning workloads go fast on a GPU?
Well, a lot of the story is really just
about memory, memory, memory.
So how do we reduce the amount of memory access we have to do?
Well, let's coalesce our memory reads together.
Let's fuse our operations together
so we don't have to read as much.
And for the things that we have to read no matter
what, well, let's reuse the memory,
so move things to shared memory and reuse it
as much as possible, which is tiling.
And then finally, maybe you can trade other resources
that you have for memory.
And that's quantization and recomputation.
So all these ideas very much relate
to this idea of memory is our bottleneck,
how do we deal with that.
Cool.
Any questions for the last thing?
Yeah.
I think we just bump up SRAM so to get rid of DRAM.
Very expensive.
I mean, there's two reasons.
One is it's just expensive to build SRAM,
also very difficult because it has to be physically close.
Signal propagation is hard.
And I think a third reason is that SRAM and DRAM are just
different storage mechanisms.
SRAM needs to be powered the whole time to hold value, very
energy hungry.
And so if you're thinking about total cost of ownership,
energy consumption, maybe you don't want a giant SRAM chip.
You really want to be using it where you need it.
Yes.
Those things scale up past 32, or if you like,
operate in chunks of 64.
You mean like, does it help if I go higher?
Yeah. No.
Because I think it's kind of as long as it divides by your burst
size, then you're good to go.
It's a divisor property.
There are other phenomena where you might get benefits
from larger divisors but not here.
Yes.
Why 108?
That's just the number of SMs.
You will have to ask Jensen for that.
I do not have an answer for you.
Yes.
So going back to the hardware side, sorry, not this part.
It just occurred in my mind.
Have you studied GPU versus Cerebras' wafer-scale engine?
Yeah.
I mean, I think sitting over there
knows much more about wafer scale stuff than I do.
We were talking about, after last lecture,
how difficult the compilation was
because if you have something wafer scale, then
you have wave interference effects and all sorts
of horrible things that happen.
That's a world that I'm not familiar with.
But I think is much more complicated than what we have here.
OK.
Cool.
All right.
So now I think we can talk about,
in some sense, the finale, which is, we've learned
a bunch of things about GPUs.
It would be nice if we can tie that all together to essentially
be able to reproduce or understand something
that I think is really important and advanced,
which is FlashAttention.
So FlashAttention is one of the big,
I think, improvements in attention capabilities in a while.
And it's all systems.
So it's going from just PyTorch's naive implementation
of attention to a single, very cleverly fused kernel.
This is from the original paper.
But you've got this dramatic improvement
in the latency of serving these things.
And as I showed you in, I think, two lectures ago,
FlashAttention is a nice, memory-efficient way
of computing things.
So you can do bigger and bigger attention.
And you can see, a lot of the gains
are going to come from improvements
in the amount of memory that is transferred from HBM,
which is the global memory.
So what do they actually do?
If you read the paper, they'll say, OK, we just do two things.
We apply tiling and recomputation.
And then we do it in a way that allows
us to do things subquadratically in the number of memory
accesses.
I think we understand all of those components now.
So let's see what's actually happening.
So remember, attention computation has a couple of things.
It has a K, Q, V. And we do a matrix multiply with the K's and the Q's.
And then we have a matrix multiply with a V at the end.
And I have a softmax in the middle.
So those are the operations that we
need to deal with-- three matrix multiplies and one softmax.
So we have matrix multiplies.
We know how to do them now.
So we're going to do a tiled matrix multiply.
Figure 1 from the paper is literally just
tiled matrix multiplies.
We've seen this before.
We're taking our inputs, our K's and Q's.
We're cutting them up.
And we're just multiplying them chunk by chunk on a tile.
And then after we do the computation, we write them out.
Nothing fancy or special here.
The thing that is tricky about FlashAttention,
and you'll see this in the assignment,
is there's a big global softmax on the whole thing.
So we can't just do this naively because the softmax
is a global operation that ties everyone together.
So it connects all of the different tiles together.
It might not seem obvious how to tile attention.
The key trick, and once you see this, this really the core,
I guess, idea or observation, once you see this,
the rest is very simple.
Normally, to compute a softmax, you
would do it this way, as shown in this plot here,
which is, you would exponentiate all of your elements.
You would subtract the maximum for numerical stability reasons.
And then you would normalize that standard softmax.
Now, there's a different way of computing this online.
And I think once you realize it, it's
kind of simple, which is, you're going to, as you go,
compute the normalized softmax.
And every time you encounter a bigger number
than what you've seen before, you're
going to swap out the maximum.
And so you have an online way of computing the softmax as you go.
The only tricky thing, of course, being the max,
and the way we deal with the max is, we keep track of the max.
And then we swap it out and correct for it every time we
see a new maximum.
Otherwise, this is really just an online running sum
of an exponential from everything that we've seen before.
And of course, at the end, you'll
just divide everything by the accumulator
that you've computed online.
Now, the important thing about the softmax
is because it's online and it goes
kind of block by block or piece by piece,
we can compute this tile by tile.
I don't need to see the rest of the tiles
in order to compute this.
I can compute the softmax for my tile.
And then I can save the partial results,
maybe write them back to global memory,
and then just continue on with my day.
So this allows us to now break up all the different interacting
pieces into something simpler.
I think this was from FlashAttention 2 or maybe 3.
I think it's 2.
I like this visualization, which shows you
which parts are being tiled.
So the dashed blocks are being done, tiled in SRAM.
The blue boxes are the ones that are in high-bandwidth memory,
the global memory.
And what you see is-- let's say, we do the K, Q inner product.
These are tiled matrix multiplies.
And they're stored in SRAM.
And we keep them in the SRAM.
And we compute this exponential.
And then similarly, in this tile,
we're going to compute this running softmax.
And I'm going to move to my next tile.
And I'm going to do the same thing.
But now I'm going to keep the partial running sums
of my softmax as I go.
I can keep them in shared memory or in registers or elsewhere.
This is a very small number of things to keep track of.
At the end, after I've computed all
these exponentiated quantities and my normalizers,
it's very simple to just multiply it with a V,
once again in the tile form, and then divide at the very end.
This allows me to essentially take the attention operation,
cut it up into these small tiled chunks, and then go.
Finally, you've got fusion.
You're going to do both of these together as much as you can
without going back and forth.
And then I'm not going to cover this or talk about it.
But what you can do is, you can, in the backward pass,
recompute everything that you need.
So the last piece of FlashAttention
is, if you saved your activations,
you still have this N squared-sized activation
that you're going to need to save for your attention.
Instead of saving that, throw it all away
and recompute everything tile by tile on the backward pass.
So it's got that recomputation piece as well.
That gives you FlashAttention.
Now we've seen all the different tricks in action.
And that's essentially all there is.
A lot of the tricks that you see for efficient implementation
and how to use GPUs well boil down to those kinds of ideas.
So to put it all back together, important to understand
the hardware.
The hardware, in our case, the GPU,
is powering scale and compute.
And we need to understand, really,
all the way to the low-level details
to fully grasp why we make certain decisions.
I don't want you guys to be the kind of people
that cargo cult 32 multipliers for your matrices.
I want you to really understand why we do those things.
And that goes all the way down, in my opinion,
to the hardware level.
The other thing is that the current way that compute
is growing means that we really want to think about matmuls.
Those are the core operations that
are very arithmetically dense.
And because of the gap between compute and memory,
we need to think very carefully about data movement.
And then finally, things like flash attention, I think,
are really cool.
There's also architecture work that's very hardware-aware.
Thinking carefully about the hardware
when we do things like architecture design
is critical to good performance for future systems.
Thanks.
[APPLAUSE]